# René L. Warren

warrenlr@gmail.com

778-386-4192

www.renewarren.ca

## Objective: Lead group to realize the potential of genomics

I am a Coordinator, Researcher and Senior Bioinformatician with over 20 years experience in biotechnology, genomics and computing research. I have played a central role in managing the bioinformatics of large international collaborations to decrypt the genomes of *Rhodococus*, spruce and bullfrog. I developed the first program for genome assembly with short DNA sequences and pioneered the development of genomics technologies that enabled the discovery of *Fusobacterium* in colon cancer, one of *Time Magazine*'s top ten medical breakthrough of 2011.

I currently lead the BC Genome Sciences Centre's bioinformatics technology lab high-performance computing group and I am eager to take on additional challenges and leadership.

### Language spoken and written: Français and English

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Sep 2013 – Present **Bioinformatics Coordinator** 

BC Cancer Agency - Genome Sciences Centre, Vancouver BC

- Provide project leadership, expertise and guidance
- Plan and coordinate activities of the group
- · Ensure project deliverables and timelines are met
- · Report progress to stakeholders
- Lead the final research manuscript of Genome Canada funded White Spruce genome sequencing project
- Lead / support manuscript writing efforts, data analysis coordination
- Peer-review manuscripts for journals Bioinformatics & BMC bioinformatics
- · Drive / assist in writing research proposals
- Supervise / Mentor a team of computational biologists and programmers
- Interview job candidates, teach and train personnel
- Support legacy bioinformatics software

Jul 2013 – Sep 2013

## Research Biologist

Canadian Food Inspection Agency (CFIA), Ottawa ON

- Commenced building CFIA's capacity in genomics and bioinformatics for early detection of pathogens and support Canada's food safety mandate
- Liaised with stakeholders for acquisition of dedicated internet network

Apr 2010 – May 2013

### Bioinformatics Coordinator

BC Cancer Agency - Genome Sciences Centre, Vancouver BC

- Lead bioinformatics software development and research
- Published research in reputed journals and at international conferences
- Peer-review manuscripts for journals Bioinformatics & BMC bioinformatics
- Wrote research proposals for grant application
- Trained employees and graduate students

# Jan 2002 – Computational Biologist Mar 2010 BC Cancer Agency – Genome

BC Cancer Agency - Genome Sciences Centre, Vancouver BC

- Lead the development of internationally acclaimed software
- Published research in reputed journals and at international conferences
- Managed the bioinformatics team that decrypted the first bacterial (*R. jostii* RHA1) and fungal (*C. gattii*) genome sequenced in Canada
- Worked in collaboration with teams on federally funded projects
- Designed/implemented databases to manage data from large-scale genomics projects
- Developed marketing material such as web portals and news release
- Supervised a team of computational biologists and programmers
- Liaised with principal investigators / project stakeholders (genomeBC)
- Wrote bioinformatics statements of work to support research
- Interviewed job candidates, taught and trained employees

# Jan 2000 – Technical Officer Dec 2001 National Passageh Co

National Research Council - Biotechnology Research Institute, Montreal QC

- Co-engineered a new system for regulating gene expression in cells
- Rescued this project from failing course
- Work led to a patent and the technology sold to a company in late 2001
- Designed, fabricated and tested components of the DNA gene switch
- Worked with teams to integrate technology in other systems (viral, cell)

#### **EDUCATION**

Sep 2005 – Jun 2006	People and Project Management Courses Provincial Health Services Authority of British Columbia, Canada
Sep 2000 – Dec 2001	Computer Science Courses Concordia University, Montréal, Canada
Jun 1997 – Aug 1999	M.Sc. Biochemistry & Molecular Biology University of British Columbia, Vancouver, Canada Studies of the regulation of rod photoreceptors cGMP-gated channels
Sep 1994 – May 1997	<b>B.Sc. Biochemistry,</b> dean Honour list mention in 1995 and 1996 Université de Montréal, Montréal, Canada Structure-function studies of the transcription factor Nkx2-5

# ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

TIONAL INFORMATION		
2015	Recipient of the John Jambor Knowledge Fund, 23 <sup>rd</sup> Conference on Intelligent Systems for Molecular Biology	
2011	Interviewed with channel NTN24 for Fusobacterium discovery in human colorectal carcinoma	
2009	Interviewed with The Scientist for work on profiling T-cell metagenomes	
2009	Assembly software SSAKE packaged in the Debian operating system	
2009	One of 6 experts invited by <i>Genome Technology</i> magazine to discuss next-generation sequencing	
2008	The president of the <i>International Society for Computational Biology</i> (ISCB) recognized SSAKE as one of 27 publications with the most impact in translational bioinformatics	
2007	Interviewed by <i>GenomeWeb</i> for the development of SSAKE, the first software for assembling next-generation DNA sequences. Software gained international recognition	
2004	Article "Warren R et al, 2004", a recommended read by the faculty of 1000	
1998	University of British Columbia Graduate Fellowship (UGF) awarded for MSc	
1997	Excellence award from the Fonds de la recherche en santé du Québec (FRSQ) for thesis	
1996	Bursary from the FRSQ for the initiation of BSc honour's research project	
1995	Worked at NASA to coordinate the crystallization of proteins under microgravity [CMIX-4 payload, space shuttle Endeavour]	
SENTATION	S (International conferences)	
2016 2015	Intelligent Systems for Molecular Biology (ISMB) Orlando, USA - <b>talk</b> Intelligent Systems for Molecular Biology (ISMB) Dublin, Ireland - <b>talks</b>	
012, 2015	Pacific Symposium on Biocomputing, Kona, Hawaii, USA – poster	

## PRES

2016 2015	Intelligent Systems for Molecular Biology (ISMB) Orlando, USA - <b>talk</b> Intelligent Systems for Molecular Biology (ISMB) Dublin, Ireland - <b>talks</b>
2012, 2015	Pacific Symposium on Biocomputing, Kona, Hawaii, USA – poster
2010	Sequencing, Finishing and Analysis in the Future, Santa Fe, New Mexico, USA – <b>talk</b>
2009	Advances in Genome Biology and Technology, Marco Island, Florida, USA – <b>2 posters</b>
2008	Pacific Symposium on Biocomputing, Kona, Hawaii, USA – poster
2007	Synthetic Biology 3.0 conference, Zürich, Switzerland – talk
2005	5th CSHL/Wellcome Trust Genome Informatics meeting. Cold Spring Harbor, NY, USA – <b>poster</b>
2004	7th Annual Conference on Computational Genomics. Reston, Virginia, USA – <b>poster</b>
2004	Genomes 2004: International Conference on Microbial Genomes. Hinxton, UK 2004 – <b>poster</b>
2003	3rd CSHL/Wellcome Trust Genome Informatics meeting. Cold Spring Harbor, NY, USA – <b>poster</b>

### **PUBLICATIONS** (selected, from 40)

- **Warren RL**, *et al.* (2015) LINKS: Scalable, alignment-free scaffolding of draft genomes with long reads. GigaScience 4:35
- Brown SD, **Warren RL**, *et al.* (2014) Neo-antigens predicted by tumor genome meta-analysis correlate with increased patient survival. Genome Res. 24:743-50
- **Warren RL**, *et al.* (2013) Co-occurrence of anaerobic bacteria in colorectal carcinomas. Microbiome. 1:16
- **Warren RL**, *et al.* (2012) Derivation of HLA types from shotgun sequence datasets. Genome Med. 4:95
- Castellarin M\*, **Warren RL**\*, *et al.* (2012) Fusobacterium nucleatum infection is prevalent in human colorectal carcinoma. Genome Res. 22:299-306 \*equal contributions
- **Warren RL**, Holt RA (2011) Targeted assembly of short sequence reads. PLoS ONE 6(5): e19816
- **Warren RL**, Holt RA (2010) A census of mutational epitopes suitable for immunologic cancer control. *Hum Immunol.* 71:245
- **Warren RL**, *et al.* (2009) Profiling model T cell metagenomes with short reads. *Bioinformatics*. 25:458
- **Warren RL**, *et al.* (2008) Transcription of foreign DNA in Escherichia coli. *Genome Res.* 18:1798
- **Warren RL**, *et al.* (2007) Assembling millions of short DNA sequences using SSAKE. *Bioinformatics*. 23:500
- Mullick A, Xu Y, **Warren R**, *et al.* (2006) The Cumate gene-switch: a system for regulated expression in mammalian cells. *BMC Biotechnology*. 6:43
- **Warren R**, *et al.* (2006) Physical map-assisted whole-genome shotgun sequence assemblies. Genome Res. 16:768
- McLeod MP, **Warren RL**, *et al.* (2006) The complete genome of Rhodococcus sp. RHA1 provides insights into a catabolic powerhouse. *Proc Nat Acad Sci USA*.103:15582
- **Warren RL**, *et al.* (2005) Management and visualization of whole genome shotgun assemblies using SAM. *Biotechniques*. 38:715
- **Warren R**, et al. (2004) Functional characterization of a catabolic plasmid from polychlorinated-biphenyl-degrading *Rhodococcus* sp. strain RHA1. *J Bacteriol*. 186:7783
- **Warren R**, Molday RS. (2002) Regulation of the photoreceptor cyclic nucleotide-gated channel. *Adv Exp Med Biol.* 514:205
- Durocher D, Charron F, **Warren R**, Schwartz RJ, Nemer M. (1997) The cardiac transcription factors Nkx2-5 and GATA-4 are mutual cofactors. *EMBO J* .16:5687

#### **PATENTS**

E Allen-Vercoe, R Holt, R Moore, R Warren

Detection of fusobacterium in a gastrointestinal sample to diagnose gastrointestinal cancer US Patent App. 13/877,421 / WO Patent 2,012,045,150

#### REFERENCES

Available upon request